Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 9 -- Letters to Franklin 1787-1790 Mss.B.F85inventory09
American Philosophical Society
- Letters to Benjamin Franklin
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 May 30; A.L.S. 4p.; Gardoqui, Diego
    Complaining of the conduct of the principal officers in the Custom house, in threatening an innocent man and showing protection to a lawless set of infamous smugglers; states the case in detail.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 June 4; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Bond, Phineas Jr. Philadelphia
    So far, has not been able to find the desired pamphelts. Sends him the Asylum for Fugitive Pieces [London, 1787], in which are some good things and a great deal of trash; recommends discretion in reading certain parts to his fair friends.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 June 6; A.L.S. 3p.; Tyler, John. Philadelphia
    Account of being cheated and robbed by his one-time partner, James Pearson; begs Franklin to find him some kind of employment; offers to work in his house or in Mr. [Benjamin Franklin] Bache's letter foundry.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 June 8; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Croker, Rev Temple Henry
    Introducing himself as the reader in Temple Church in 1761, and author of a treatise on Magnetism; desires the honor of a short interview.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 June 9; A.L.S. 1p.; Coxe, Tench. Philadelphia
    Several foreigners elected honorary members of the Society for the Relief of Free Negroes; enclosing the brief letters informing them of their election, with a request for Franklin's signature.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 June 11; A.L.S. 1p.; Phile, Frederick. Philadelphia
    Enclosing a true statement of the transactions between Mr. John Leamy and himself concerning the passport of the schooner "Regla."
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 June 13; A.L.S. 4p.; Le Veillard, Louis Guillaume
    Sends him a work by M. de Volney; introducing the bearer of it, M. Saugrain [ de Vigny], a young savant, to Franklin's notice. Reasons why M. De la Valette gave up his intended trip to America. Again urges him to write his memories. American politics; the National Convention; question of imposts and custom-houses; attitude of certain states like Rhode Island in refusing to send Deputies. Regretting Franklin's failure to send his paper on the retention by the English of the posts on the American frontier. Question of paper money. Per cent, paid on investments in real estate in America. Affairs in France; Archbishop of Toulouse made Minister and President of the Council of Finances; M. de Villedeuil made Controller-General; M. de Vergenne's memory somewhat tarnished; work accomplished by the Assemblé des Notables; suppression of the corvées; new taxes levied. Expects to dine with Mr. [Thomas] Paine at M. [Le Ray] de Chaumont's. Return of Mr. [Thomas] Jefferson. Absence of the Due de la Rochefoucauld and all his family. Death of M. Brillon. News of other friends.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 June 18; A.L.S. 10p.; Guillotin, Joseph Iguace. Paris
    Their work together in exposing charlatanism and imposture. Reminding him of the many questions concerning America with which he used to bombard him at Passy; his desire to emigrate there shared by many of his friends; disgusted with the despotism, superstition and wickedness of France; their wish to establish a settlement on the Ohio river, the home of equality, liberty and friendship; they number a dozen men, some with families, some without; some rich, some poor; among them they can boast of a knowledge of the sciences and useful arts; introducing two of their number, M. Picque and M. Saugrain [de Vigny] who are to be the pioneers of their party; begs for them Franklin's advice, protection and recommendation; flattering account of his brother-in-law, M. Saugrain [de Vigny].
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 June 19; A.L.S. 3p.; Gardoqui, James (Diego)
    Acknowledging Franklin's favor of the 11th inst. with the report of the Officer of the Custom-houses regarding the schooner, "Regla"; his object was not to injure the officer but to protect the United States against smugglers. Need of a treaty between America and Spain.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 June 19; A.L.S. 3p.; D'Arect, -----. Paris
    Recommending M. Saugrain; the recent death of his friend, Don [Bernard] Galvez, Viceroy of Mexico, frustrated his hopes of fame and fortune in that country; his work in the chemical laboratory in Paris; his object in going to America is to choose a site for permanent settlement.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 June 19; L.S. 4p.; Choctaw Chief and Chickesaw Captain
    Desiring such directions as will enable them to proceed with their business.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 June 21; A.L. 4p.; Le Roy, Julien David. Paris
    Delighted at the report of Franklin's health received from Mr. [Thomas] Paine; amazed at the amount of work he is able to accomplish. Messages from [Comte] de Buffon, who is still a great sufferer. Mr. Paine's desire to see a balloon ascension; M. [François] Blanchard the only exponent of that art at present. M. [Jean Baptiste Marie] Meusnier's book not yet printed.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 June 22; A.L.S. 4p.; Paine, Thomas. Paris
    Account of his trip from Havre-de-Grace to Paris; his cordial reception by Franklin's friends; kindness of M. Le Roy. Exhibition of fire-works at [ Comte] de Buffon's. His model of a bridge not yet arrived; introduced to M. Terenet, the bridge architect.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, X, 310; Bigelow, IX, 393).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 June 22; A.L.S. 1p.; Carmichael, William. Madrid
    Acknowledging his election as a member of the [American] Philosophical Society; enclosing letters of acknowledgment from the Count de Campomanès and Don [Joseph] Miguel [de] Flores; forwarded the books mentioned in those letters.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 June 23; A.L. 3p.; Le Roy, Mme
    Account of the cruel treatment accorded her by her husband, and of her unchanging devotion to him; left him six months before; miserably unhappy. Disavows any courage in making the ascent in a balloon; wishes it might have carried her to Franklin for whom she has the greatest love and admiration. Her friendship with Mme. Helvétius.
    Printed in Putnam's Monthly, Jan., 1907, 432.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 June 26; A.L.S. 2p.; January, Benjamin. Philadelphia
    Offering to rebind all the books which were misplaced through the carelessness of a journeyman.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1787.] June 27; L. 1p.; The Gentlemen of the Constitutional Convention at the Indian Queen
    Invitating the President of the State of Pennsylvania to dinner at their quarters.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 June 28; A.L.S. 1p.; Knox, General Henry. Philadelphia
    Acknowledging Franklin's application on behalf of M. Varranault, for admission into the Society of the Cincinnati; necessary for the gentleman to address himself to the Society in France.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 July 2; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Churchman, John. East Nottingham, Pa
    Desiring to be informed, through his brother, Mordecai Churchman, in Philadelphia, if the Astronomer Royal at Greenwich writes anything respecting the affair sent to him three months ago.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 July 3; A.L.S. 1p.; Small, Alexander. London
    Hoped Franklin would have retained some of Mirabeau's patriotic principles; opposed to taxes on imports; thinks Philadelphia should be made a free port; objects to the loyalists being banished; sees nothing of the liberal disposition of Dr. Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 July 3; A.L.S. Ezra Stiles, Correspond[in]g Secretary.; The Connecticut Society Academy of Arts and Sciences. New Haven
    A literary society instituted the previous year, entitled the Connecticut Academy of Arts and Sciences, of which Lieutenant-Governor [Oliver] Wolcott is President; directed by the Society to apply to the [American] Philosophical Society and the Academies of science throughout Europe for their publications; in return will send their literary collections when these shall be published.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 July 9; A.L.S. 2p.; Lotbinière, Chartier de, marquis de
    On Mr. [John] Jay's advice, came to America in order to obtain possession of his estates on Lake Champlain; if affairs turn out as he now has reason to hope, will remain indefinitely in America; his impatience to see Franklin only held in check by the report of the heat in Philadelphia.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 July 14; A.L.S. 5p.; Lettsom, John Coakley. London
    To the memoir of Dr. [John] Fothergill, he has annexed memoirs of some of his associates; his wish to have introduced some anecdotes of Franklin; the importance of such memorials. Discovery by a man, called Borth, of a method of imitating paintings in oil; facsimiles of famous paintings finished in a few hours; the method known only to Borth and a Mr. Johnson, a rich quaker; report that he has been offered £60,000 for his secret; conjectures concerning the method employed. Is cultivating a plant called in France, racine de disette; no more prolific vegetable known; promises to send a description with seeds. Begs Franklin's kind offices on behalf of a clergyman, Mr. George Hunt, who desires the honor of Doctor of Divinity from the College of Philadelphia.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 July 16; The Medical Society of London. London
    Certificate of Membership.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 July 18; A.L.S. 3p.; Buffon, Comte de
    Acknowledging the seeds and rare plants sent him for the King's garden. Desires to hear of the progerss of the [American] Philosophical Society. Just finished his Histoire Naturelle de Minéraux; offers to send it to the Society. Is printing a treatise on the properties and use of the magnet. Desires to know what remedy Franklin found most efficacious for the stone.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, X, 312; Bigelow, XI, 398).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 July 19; A.L.S. 2p.; Forman, Ezekiel. Auburn
    Sending Franklin a curious puzzle from Signor Falconi from New York; explains the position of the three sticks and the adjustment arranged by Falconi; promises further information, if desired.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 July 26; A.L.S. 1p.; West, Benjamin. London
    Arrival of Mr. [Samuel] Jennings with Franklin's letter of recommendation; the young gentleman's fame for painting had already preceded him; will give him every assistance in his power. News of his family. Mr. [Caleb] Whitefoord's desire to hear from Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 July 27; A.L.S. 4p.; La Roche, Abbé de
    Necessary to communicate with Franklin as the devout commune with celestial substances; their sacrifice in giving him up to America; their pleasure to imagine that he will be the one benefactor of men to escape their ingratitude. Account of a fête given in honor of the Lady of Auteuil [Madame Helvétius]; French politics; results of the Assemblé des Notables; disordered state of finance; misery of the people; difficult to foresee the outcome. Affairs in Holland. Visit from the Archbishop of Bordeaux; much talk of Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 July 31; A.L.S. 1p.; Stiles, Ezra. Yale College
    Acknowledging Franklin's favor of the 14th inst. with the list of Philosophical Societies in Europe; discouraged by his advice to wait until they can send forth a volume themselves, before applying for publications from learned Societies; fears this will mean a long delay. Delighted to see an example of the new method of taking copies of papers from the originals. Acknowledging the second volume of the Transactions of the American Philosophical Society.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 July 31; A.L.S. 1p.; Steele, Joshua. Kendal's Plantation in Barbados
    Has been in Barbados over seven years looking after estates there.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 July 31; A.L.S. 8p.; Morellet, abbé
    Pleasure derived from Franklin's letters by the whole "Academy of Auteuil." Religious toleration. Commercial regulations as to imposts and taxation; opposed to duties on foreign merchandise. Affairs in France; praises the Archbishop of Toulouse, the new Minister of Finance, Madame Helvétius; amusing account of their sufferings from her cats. Mr. [Thomas] Jefferson's work [Notes on Virginia] the Abbé [Morellet] translated, much liked. [Thomas] Paine's model of an iron bridge. Demand for an Assembly of the States-General. Messages from friends.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, X, 313; Bigelow, IX, 399).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 August 1; A.L.S. 1p.; Du Plessis, Thomas-Antoine Mauduit. Paris
    Account of a serious illness which brought him to death's door and caused him great fear. Messages from the Count d'Estaing, who has done all in his power for Franklin's freind, Mr. [Thomas] Paine. Trouble in Holland; fear of war; influence of Mr. [William] Pitt in England against anything which will mar the present peace.
    (In French. In duplicate.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 August 2; A.L.S. 1p.; Nesmoz and Valliant. Philadelphia
    Understands that Franklin sometimes has occasion to draw upon Paris; desires to know if he will oblige them with bills to the amount of three or four thousand livres, and upon what terms?
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 August 5; A.L.S. 2p.; Guillotin, Joseph Ignace
    Request for Franklin's advice and assistance on behalf of Messrs. Picque and Saugrain [de Vigny]; begs him to recommend their inexperience to a capable adviser wherever they go; Illinois likely to be chosen as their place of settlement; understands from Mr. [Thomas] Jefferson that grants of land may be had there.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 August 7; A.L.S. 2p.; Vaughan, Samuel Jr. New York
    Sending him the Judiciary Bill and the bill for the punishment of certain crimes; question of the power invested in Congress; the members cautious lest their measures should not meet with the approbation of their constituents. Enclosing a report of the Assembly in Jamaica on the slave trade and slavery in that Island.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 August 8; L. in 3d P. 1p.; North, Major William. New York
    Enclosing an important letter for Mr. Williams.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 August 9; A.L.S. 1p.; Rumford, Jonathan. Wilmington
    Reported in 1777 that Franklin sent Congress a package of all clean sheets of paper; sends him something similar with the hope that he and Washington will fill them. Expects the gentlemen of the Convention to carry out the terms of every treaty America has made.
    A. E. by Franklin. "Jonathan Rumford--crack'd."
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 August 15; A.L.S. 3p.; Le Roy, Jean Baptiste
    Praise for Mr. [Thomas] Paine; has been appointed, by the Academy, one of the Commissioners to examine his design; delay in preparing their report; thinks his model has certain advantages over the others presented. Sir Joseph Banks's election to membership in the Academy.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 August 16; A.L.S. 1p.; Croker, Temple Henry. Christopher
    Sending Franklin his old pamphlet on Magnctism; introducing Mr. Clifton. After the hurricane months, proposes trying Franklin's improvement on his horizontal wind-mill.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 August 16 and 1788 January 14; A.L.S. Samuel Osgood, Arthur Lee. [In the second letter the name of Walter Livingston substitutes that of Arthur Lee.] 4p.; The Board of Treasury
    Relative to the account of John Ross against the United States.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 August 17; A.L.S. 1p.; Whitehurst, John. London
    Sends his little attempt towards obtaining invariable measures; offer of Dr. [Nevil] Maskelyne to keep the machine under his inspection at the Observatory, in order to authenticate its going.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 August 19; A.L.S. 3p.; Burdett, P.P. Carlsruhe
    Reminds Franklin of his appreciation of the medal struck on account of the American peace. Introducing M. de Schilling, a gentleman of birth, education and honor, who served with distinction in the army of the King of Sardinia; his present wish to settle in America and engage in agriculture or commerce.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 August 20; A.L.S. 4p.; La Rochefoucauld, Louis Alexandre, duc de
    Regrets being absent from Paris during Mr. [Thomas] Paine's visit; the interest the Academy will take in his model for a bridge. Impatient to hear the result of the Convention called together to revise the Constitution; high hopes for an Assembly which numbers Franklin and Washington among its members. Agrees with him on the instability of popular favor; believes Franklin's case, will prove the exception. French affairs; result of the Assemblè des Notables; the formation of Provincial Assemblies; the Marquis [de la Fayette] and himself both elected members from different Provinces.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 August 21; A.L.S. 1p.; Childs, Francis
    Humble apology for again postponing certain payments due Franklin; proposes to come to Philadelphia and draw up and a new agreement. Business of the printing office.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 August 24; A.L.S. 2p.; Smith, John. Philadelphia
    Concerning the estate of the late Robert Smith, carpenter, of which he is administrator; has settled all the accounts except the one with Franklin; suggests a method by which the money can be paid.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 August 25; A.L.S. 7p.; Newenham, Sir Edward. Roxborough
    Account of successful experiments in agriculture tried by Mr. Kirwan; slothfulness and apathy of the Irish peasantry; has endeavored in vain to convert them to these new methods of raising crops. Promising to send the car by the first opportunity. Completion of their city canal. Meeting of volunteer regiments; threats to disperse them; expects to visit the encampment incognito and drink the health of American patriots, with success to the Convention; rails against Rhode Island for not sending delegates. Affairs in Holland. Advice to America, should a European war break out in consequence of Dutch or Brabant politics; disapproves of England's attitude in taking the Stadtholder's part. Enormous addition of taxes and pensions. His trip to America delayed by a tiresome law-suit.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 August 30; A.L. in 3d P. 1p; Lathrop, Dr. John
    Requesting his acceptance of a discourse given before the Humane Society of Boston; encouraged by Mrs. [Jane] Mecom to make himself known to Dr. Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 September 5; A.L.S. 1p.; Biddle, Charles. Philadelphia
    Sending Franklin the message for the General Assembly, in case he wishes to make any alterations.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 September 5; L.S. 1p.; Wharton, Samuel. Philadelphia
    Prevented by illness from waiting on Franklin. Asks for an introduction to his son, Richard Wharton, Attorney-at-law, to Colonel [John] Armstrong, President of Court of Quarter Sessions in Armstrong County; his intention to settle in Dauphin County and practice law.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 September 8; A.L.S. 2p.; Moreau de St. Méry, -----
    For thirteen years has been engaged on different works relative to the French Colonies; his ardent desire to become a member of the [American] Philosophical Society; offers to send the first five volumes of a work which he thinks will prove of interest to America; expects to return to France in May. Recalls his introduction to Franklin by Dr. [Matthew] Maty in London.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 September 10; A.N. 3d P. 1p.; Baldwin Mr. Philadelphia
    Accepting Franklin's invitation for dinner on Wednesday.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 September 11; A.L.S. 1p.; Lenox, David. Philadelphia
    Begs leave to renew in person his request to Franklin for a certain appointment.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 September 12; A.L.S. 2p.; Sevier, John. Franklin
    Delighted with his friendly attitude towards their young republic. Predatory excursions of the Creek Indians; so far their frontier has been unmolested.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 September 14; A.L.S. 3p.; Whatley, George. London
    Enclosing memorial relative to Francis Dashwood [Baron Le Despencer]. Question of banks, paper money and coining. Criticism of a publication dedicated to Mr. [John] Adams, entitled Political Sketches. Interested in the result of the [Constitutional] Convention. Their relative ages. News of their friend. Dr. [William] Rowley.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 September 20; A.L.S. 3p.; Le Roy, Julien David. Havre
    Experiments in navigation; sure of the success of this new kind of vessel; the simplification and perfecting of his system of sails; offers to arrage this new style of rigging on any ship sent from America to Roucn Havre. Introducing M. Le Roux.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 September 20; A.L.S. 2p.; Macnamara, James. Philadelphia
    Account of his being shipwrecked on his passage from Ireland to America; his wife and child drowned and everything else lost; is now a sufferer from epileptic fits, the result of his grief and terror; cared for by the managers and physicians of the Pennsylvania Hospital; begs Franklin for a change of clothes, as he is destitute of everything.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 September 20; L.S. 4P.; Thomas, -----. Florence
    Account of merchandise sent in 1783 through Mr. [Jonathan] Williams [Jr.], to Bache and Shee at Philadelphia, to be sold on commission; has never received but a small part of the profits of that sale; gives the details of the affair; if Franklin refuses to intercede, must endeavor to obtain justice in a more public manner.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 September 24; A.L.S. 3p.; Carey, Mathew. Philadelphia
    Concerning the purchase from him of type; takes exception to a remark of Franklin made during their interview on this subject.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 September 26; A.L.S. 4p.; Price, Richard. Hackney
    Acknowledging his election as member of the Pennsylvania Society for abolishing negro slavery; similar institution just founded in London. Waiting for an account of the [Constitutional] Convention. Spirit of liberty beginning to prevail in Europe as a result of the American war. Departure of Mr. [John] Paradise and family for Virginia. Report of war between Turkey and Russia. Rumor of the King of Prussia having entered Holland and reinstated the Stadtholder in all his powers.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, X, 320; Bigelow, IX, 411).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 September 28; A.L.S. 4p.; Ingenhousz, Jan
    Desires Mr. [John] Williams to finish up the business of his loan-receipts and send him over the money. Finds fault with the American postal service. Question of the money due him by Mr. [Samuel] Wharton; convinced that Franklin's powerful influence can obtain justice for him. Dismal outlook for Europe; distracted state of his own country; the English at the bottom of it; Turkish war probably blown up from the same quarter.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 October 9; A.L.S. 2p.; Jennings, Samuel. London
    Delighted with his reception by Mr. [Benjamin] West, who is at Windsor, finishing the paintings designed for the Castle; much impressed so far by the elegant performances in the Fine Arts; especially struck with the statuary in Westminster Abbey.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 October 10; A.L.S. 1p.; Ehlers, M. Kiel
    Hopes he received the first volume of a work, of which he now sends the second.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 October 10; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Sr
    Thanking Franklin for the plan of government sent him; thinks it the best that could be formed under the present circumstances; influence exerted against it. News of Mrs. [Jane] Mccom.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 October 13; A.L.S. 2p.; Du Pont de Nemours, Pierre Samuel, 1739-1817